

## **PROFILE**

# Inquisitive, imaginative, intuitive and insightful

An astute strategist with many hats and 10 years experience working in the B2B & B2C sectors. Blending insights and creativity to create compelling strategies that unlock untapped potential for brands whilst creating value in people's lives. Passionately striving to transform businesses into the market disruptors, brand leaders and world shapers of the future. Seeking an opportunity in an organisation that unequivocally empowers and champions my skills and experience as a brand leader whilst sharing my belief that branding should be used as a positive force for businesses, people and the planet.

#### PRESENT EXPERIENCE

# Senior Strategist - MRM Mc Cann - (Freelance to Perm) May, 2021 till Present

MRM London is a leading customer relationship agency that is focused on helping brands grow meaningful relationships with people using the power of creativity, the beauty of data, and the magic of technology. I'm currently engaged in two capacities at MRM, one as an experience strategist on a number of accounts such as Cisco, Halfords, Mitsubishi Electric, Panasonic and Sanofi as well the lead digital strategist on Vauxhall.

#### Key responsibilities:

- User experience planning and relationship mapping
- Playing a senior role in developing innovative, data-driven, multi-dimensional strategies and tactics to improve customer and business outcomes for strategic CRM client engagements, and an implementation lead role in helping bring those strategies to life
- Developing brand communication strategies
- Overseeing projects to follow guidelines and are delivered on time
- Integrating digital assets, raising brand awareness, collaborating on marketing campaigns, leading digital activation projects, and measuring the efficiency and effectiveness of digital channelsCompleting competitive audits, qualitative interviews and reports
- Writing up and briefing creatives teams

## RECENT EXPERIENCE

# Senior Strategist - Pollitt & Partners - Sept, 2020 till May 2021

Founded in 1987, Pollitt and Partners are a brand agency 100% owned by the people who work here. Collaborating with clients to define, create and activate their brands. My experience to date spans organisations in the Healthcare Packaging, Logistics, Real Estate and Animal Charity sectors.

# Key responsibilities:

- Designing interviews, writing up discussion guides, conducting research, writing debriefs as required in all work streams
- Creative copywriting and brand transformation strategies for Mölnlycke, a Swedish Meditech company
- Brand idea and proposition development, crafting key messages and brand narratives for World Animal Protection
- Brand naming and creative ideation for a number of property developments in London such as Homes for Lambeth
- Supporting the new business director on pitches, tenders submissions and other research as required by the business

# Lead Creative Strategist - Notepad Studio - Apr, 2018 till Aug, 2020

Notepad is an independent branding agency which accelerates growth through brand, culture, and design. As the lead creative strategist I headed up the studio's strategic offer for our Birmingham and London clients. As a team we developed engaging brand strategies which created tangible value for our clients and their customers. In a largely remote role I was responsible for driving 3-4 projects in tandem, supporting and coaching junior strategists and leading the brand ideation initiatives both inside and outside the agency.

#### Key responsibilities:

- Crafting brand names, personality, purpose, proposition, positioning, personas, customer journeys and architecture
- Developing and writing brand concepts, narratives and big ideas to inspire and excite stakeholders
- Preparing for new business pitches and winning the agency work, along with up-selling other branding services
- Designing brand models, organisational systems and value platforms for commercial clarity and future proofing
- Writing anywhere from short to long form copy for both client work and internal publications The Gist
- Moving the business and our clients into alternative revenue streams and new opportunity areas
- Leading in-house CSR initiatives, such as the development of www.wearesometime.org.

#### CONTRACTING EXPERIENCE

Creative Strategist - Brand Folk Ltd - Nov, 2013 till Apr, 2018

My first few formative years I developed my skills as brand strategist in agencies including Landor (Lavazza & Barclays Bank), Bluemarlin (Shell Oil), Bulletproof (Heineken, Campari & CocaCola), Little Bird (Campari & Tribute Ale) and with Design Bridge on Diageo (Guinness), PepsiCo, Unilever (Hellmann's and Lipton Iced team) and JTI. After a solid stint in FMCG, I went on to found Brand Folk Ltd worked as independent creative strategist. It enabled me to explore alternative agencies, environments and approaches. Over the course of 3 years I have developed my expertise as a creative thinker and brand builder. With time I amassed a strong network of contacts, earning myself some strong recommendations as can be found on Linked In and built up a portfolio work in the FMCG, Retail, Education, Property, Startup and Service design sectors. All these are available on request

#### Key responsibilities:

- Quickly settling into any office environment and getting to grips with brand challenges at pace
- Using research, insight creation and brand narratives to get brands closer to their customers
- Leading client workshops and moderating customer/ user interviews
- Developing strategic frameworks and writing consumer-facing messaging with bespoke TOV and brand personality
- Translating consumer insights and brand strategy into convincing brand concepts and creative leaping off points
- Putting high quality, rigorous thinking and imagination at the heart of core client challenges

#### **EXPERIENCE OVERVIEW**





forpeople notepad



Usio. Landor



SAFFRON





ry.

Bulletproof. FITC

& Partners

**Pollitt** 





# bluemarlin EY Seren YourStudio DesignBridge.



#### **EDUCATION**



# MSc in Brand Leadership (with Distinction) - Aug, 2013

Dissertation: Branding in the dark – Exploring how brands can reinforce their multi-sensory experiences in the absence of the visual sensory channel.

# Awarded:

- UEA prize for best dissertation
- UEA prize for best overall performance

# L-Università ta' Malta

# BA (Hons) in Tourism Management and Marketing (2.1) - May, 2010

Dissertation: Future proofing the hospitality industry through timeshare holidays.

#### Awarded:

- ITS Higher National Diploma in Hospitality Management (Merit)

#### **INTERESTS**



- Art and photography, including photo retouching
- Storytelling through film: 'The Folkster's Hat' Film Blog
- Bird watching: I'm self-proclaimed bird nerd and a member of BirdLife Malta and the RSPB
- Reading literature on sensory branding and the power of semiotics
- Animal welfare and protection, campaigning to ban hunting in Malta
- Cycling, Hiking, Camping just about anything that gets me outdoors

**GET IN TOUCH** 

E: ian.micallef.tfh@gmail.com M: +44 07902 717 288